15 That evening, at 8:30 exquisitely dressed and wearing a large button hole
of Palmer violets, Dorian Gray was ushered into Lady nar's drawing room by bowing
servants. His forehead was throbbing with Madden nerves, and he felt wildly excited,
but his manner as he bent over his hostess’s hand was as easy and graceful as ever.
Perhaps one never seems so much at one’s ease as when one has to play a
part. Certainly no one looking at Dorian Gray that night could have believed that
he had passed through a tragedy as horrible as any tragedy of our age. Those
finely shaped fingers could never have clutched a knife for sin, nor those
smiling lips have cried out on God and goodness. He himself could not help
wondering at the calm of his demeanor and for a moment felt keenly the
terrible pleasure of a double life. It was a small party, got up rather
in a hurry by Lady narbar who was a very clever woman with what Lord Henry used
to describe as the remains of really remarkable ugliness. She had proved an excellent
wife to one of our most tedious ambassadors, and having buried her
husband properly in a marble mosum which she had herself designed, and married off
her daughters to some rich, rather elderly men, she devoted herself now to
the pleasure of French fiction, French cookery, and French espri when she could get it
get Dorian was one of her ESP special favorites and she always told him that
she was extremely glad she had not met him in early life. “I know, my dear, I
should have fallen madly in love with you,” she used to say, “and thrown my bonnet
right over the mills for your sake. It is most fortunate that you were not thought
of at the time. As it was, our bonnets were so unbecoming, and the mills were so
occupied in trying to raise the wind, that I never had even a flirtation with
anybody. However, that was all nur's fault.
He was dreadfully shortsighted and there is no pleasure in taking in a husband who never sees
anything.” Her guests this evening were rather tedious. The fact was, as she
explained to Dorian, behind a very shabby fan, one of her married daughters had
come up quite suddenly to stay with her, and, to make matters worse, had actually
brought her husband with her. “I think it is most unkind of her, my
dear,” she whispered. “Of course I go and stay with them every summer after I come
from hurg but then an old woman like me must have fresh air sometimes, and
besides, I really wake them up. You don’t know what an existence they lead down
there. It is pure unadulterated country life. They get up early, because they have
so much to do, and go to bed early, because they have so little to think about.
There has not been a scandal in the neighborhood since the time of Queen
Elizabeth, and consequently they all fall asleep after dinner. You Shan sit next to
either of them. You shall sit by me and amuse me.” Dorian murmured a graceful compliment
and looked around the room.
Yes: it was certainly a tedious party. Two of the people he had never seen before,
and the others consisted of Ernest herodan one of those middle-aged
mediocrities so common in London clubs who have no enemies, but are thoroughly
disliked by their friends; Lady ruon an overdressed woman of 47 with a hooked
nose, who was always trying to get herself compromised, but was so peculiarly plain
that to her great disappointment no one would ever believe anything against her;
Mrs Erin a pushing nobody, with a delightful lisp and Venetian red hair;
Lady Alice Chapman, his hostess’s daughter, a dowy dull girl, with one of
those characteristic British faces that, once seen, are never remembered; and her
husband, a red cheeked white whiskered creature who, like so many of his class,
was under the impression that inordinate joviality can atone for an entire lack of
ideas. He was rather sorry he had come, till Lady narbar looking at the great
omalu guilt clock that sprawled in gy curves on the mauve draped mantle Shelf
exclaimed: “How horrid of Henry Waton to be so late! I sent round to him this
morning on chance and he promised faithfully not to disappoint
me.” It was some consolation that Harry was to be there, and when the door opened
and he heard his slow musical voice lending charm to some insincere apology,
he ceased to feel bored. But at dinner he could not eat anything. Plate after plate
went away untasted. Lady narbar kept scolding him for what she called “an
insult to poor Adolf who invented the menu espcially for you,” and now and then
Lord Henry looked across at him, wondering at his silence and abstracted
manner. From time to time the butler filled his glass with champagne. He drank
eagerly, and his thirst seemed to increase. “Dorian,” said Lord Henry at last,
as the show fua was being handed round, “what is the matter with you tonight
You are quite out of sorts.” “I believe he is in love,” cried Lady
nabar and that he is afraid to tell me for fear I should be jealous heun's
quite right. I certainly should.” “Dear Lady nabar murmured Dorian,
smiling I've not been in love for a whole week— —not, in fact, since Madame deferol left
town.” “How you men can fall in love with that woman!” exclaimed the old lady. “I
really cannot understand it.” “It is simply because she remembers you
when you were a little girl, Lady narbar said Lord Henry. “She is the one link
between us and your short frocks.” “She does not remember my short
frocks at all, Lord Henry. But I remember her very well at Vienna 30 years ago, and
how decol she was then gra She is still deol he answered, taking an olive in his long
fingers; “and when she is in a very smart gown she looks like an addition Lux of a
bad French novel. She is really wonderful, and full of surprises. Her capacity for family
affection is extraordinary. When her third husband died, her hair turned quite gold from
grief.” “How can you, Harry!” cried Dorian. “It is a most romantic explanation,” laughed the
hostess. “But her third husband, Lord Henry!
You don’t mean to say Ferell is the fourth?” “Certainly, Lady narbar
I don’t believe a word of it.” “Well, ask Mr.
Gray. He is one of her most intimate friends.” “Is it true, Mr. Gray?” “She assures
me so, Lady narbar said Dorian. “I asked her whether, like margarite denar she had
their hearts embalmed and hung at her girdle. She told me she didn’t, because
none of them had had any hearts at all.” “Four husbands! Upon my word that is trop
de Trop daas tell her,” said Dorian. “Oh! she is audacious enough for
anything, my dear. And what is feral like?
I don’t know him.” “The husbands of very beautiful women belong to the criminal
classes,” said Lord Henry, sipping his wine.
Lady nabra hit him with her fan. “Lord Henry, I am not at all surprised
that the world says that you are extremely wicked.” “But what world says that?” asked
Lord Henry, elevating his eyebrows. “It can only be the next world.
This world and I are on excellent
[Music]
terms.” “Everybody I know says you are very wicked,” cried the old lady, shaking her
head. Lord Henry looked serious for some moments. “It is perfectly monstrous,” he
said, at last, “the way people go about nowadays saying things against one
behind one’s back that are absolutely and entirely true.” “Isn’t he encourageable cried Dorian,
leaning forward in his chair.
“I hope so,” said his hostess, laughing. “But really, if you all worship Madame deferol
in this ridiculous way, I shall have to marry again so as to be in the
fashion.” “You will never marry again, Lady nbar broke in Lord Henry. “You were far
too happy. When a woman marries again, it is because she detested her first
husband. When a man marries again, it is because he adored his first wife. Women
try their luck; men risk theirs NAB wasn’t perfect,” cried the old
lady. “If he had been, you would not have loved him, my dear lady,” was the rejoinder.
“Women love us for our defects. If we have enough of them, they will forgive us
everything, even our intellects. You will never ask me to dinner again after saying this I'm
afraid, Lady nbar but it is quite true.” “Of course it is true, Lord Henry. If
we women did not love you for your defects, where would you all be? Not one of you
would ever be married. You would be a set of unfortunate bachelors. Not, however,
that that would alter you much. Nowadays all the married men live like bachelors,
and all the bachelors like married men fandle murmured Lord Henry finu globe answered his
hostess. “I wish it were finu globe said Dorian with a sigh. “Life is a great disappointment.”
“Ah, my dear,” cried Lady narbar putting on her gloves, “don’t tell me that you have
exhausted life. When a man says that one knows that life has exhausted him. Lord
Henry is very wicked, and I sometimes wish that I had been; but you are made to
be good— —you look so good. I must find you
a nice wife. Lord Henry, don’t you think that Mr. Gray should get married I'm
always telling him so, Lady Nabor said Lord Henry with a bow. “Well,
we must look out for a suitable match for him. I shall go through de Brett
carefully tonight and draw out a list of all the eligible young ladies.” “With their
ages, Lady nabar asked Dorian. “Of course, with their ages, slightly edited. But
nothing must be done in a hurry. I want it to be what The Morning Post calls a
suitable alliance, and I want you both to be happy.” “What nonsense people talk about
happy marriages!” exclaimed Lord Henry. “A man can be happy with any woman, as long
as he does not love her.” “Ah! what a cynic you are!” cried the
old lady, pushing back her chair and nodding to Lady ruon You must come and
dine with me soon again. You are really an admirable tonic, much better than what
Sir Andrew prescribes for me. You must tell me what people you would like to
meet, though. I want it to be a delightful gathering.” “I like men who have a future
and women who have a past,” he answered. “Or do you think that would make it a petticoat
party?” “I fear so,” she said, laughing, as she stood up. “A thousand pardons, my dear Lady
ruon she added, “I didn’t see you hadn’t finished your
cigarette.” “Never mind, Lady narbar I smoke a great deal too much I'm going to limit
myself, for the future.” “Pray don’t, Lady ruon said Lord
Henry. “Moderation is a fatal thing. Enough is as bad as a meal. More than enough is
as good as a feast.” Lady Ruxton glanced at him curiously. “You must come and explain that
to me some afternoon, Lord Henry. It sounds a fascinating theory,” she murmured, as she
swept out of the room. “Now, mind you don’t stay too long
over your politics and scandal,” cried Lady narbar from the door. “If you do, we
are sure to squabble upstairs.” The men laughed, and Mr. Chapman
got up solemnly from the foot of the table and came up to the top. Dorian Gray
changed his seat and went and sat by Lord Henry. Mr. Chapman began to talk in a
loud voice about the situation in the House of Commons. He Gord at his
adversaries. The word doctrinaire —word full of terror to the British mind—
—reappeared from time to time between his explosions. An alliterative prefix served
as an ornament of oratory. He hoisted the Union Jack on the pinnacles of thought. The inherited
stupidity of the race— —sound English common sense he jovially termed it— —was
shown to be the proper bullwark for society. A smile curved Lord Henry’s lips,
and he turned around and looked at Dorian. “Are you better, my dear fellow?” he
asked. “You seemed rather out of sorts at dinner I'm quite well, Harry I'm tired.
That is all.” “You were charming last night. The little duchess is quite devoted to you.
She tells me she is going down to Selby.” “She has promised to come on the
20th Is Monmouth to be there, too?” “Oh, yes, Harry.” “He bores me dreadfully, almost as
much as he bores her. She is very clever, too clever for a woman. She lacks the
indefinable charm of weakness. It is the feet of clay that
make the gold of the image precious. Her feet are very pretty, but they are not
feet of clay. White porcelain feet, if you like. They have been through the fire, and
what fire does not destroy, it hardens. She has had experiences.” “How long has she been
married?” asked Dorian. “An eternity, she tells me. I believe, according to the
peage it is 10 years, but 10 years with Monmouth must have been like eternity,
with time thrown in. Who else is coming?” “Oh, the willig bees Lord Rugby and
his wife, our hostess Jeffrey Clon the usual set. I have asked Lord Grotrian.”
“I like him,” said Lord Henry. “A great many people don’t, but I find him charming. He
atones for being occasionally somewhat overdressed by being always absolutely
overeducated He is a very modern type.” “I don’t know if he will be able to
come, Harry. He may have to go to Monte Carlo with his father.” “Ah! what a nuisance
people’s people are! Try and make him come. By the way, Dorian, you ran off very
early last night. You left before 11: What did you do afterwards? Did you go straight
home?” Dorian glanced at him hurriedly and frowned. “No, Harry,” he said at last, “I did
not get home till nearly 3: Did you go to the
club?” “Yes,” he answered. Then he bit his lip.
“No I I I don’t mean that. I didn’t go to
the club. I walked about. I forget what I did.... How inquisitive you are, Harry!
You always want to know what one has been doing. I always want to forget what
I have been doing. I came in at halfast 2
if you wish to know the exact time. I had
left my latch key at home, and my servant had to let me in. If you want any
corroborative evidence on the subject, you can ask him.” Lord Henry shrugged his shoulders. “My
dear fellow, as if I cared! Let us go up to the drawing room No sherry, thank you,
Mr. Chapman. Something has happened to you, Dorian. Tell me what it is. You are not yourself
tonight Don’t mind me, Harry I'm irritable, and out of temper. I shall come
around and see you tomorrow or next day.
Make my excuses to Lady nabar I Shan go upstairs. I shall go home. I must go home.”
“All right, Dorian. I dare say I shall see you tomorrow at tea time The duess is
coming.” “I will try to be there, Harry,” he said, leaving the room. As he drove back
to his own house, he was conscious that the sense of terror he thought he had
strangled had come back to him. Lord Henry’s casual questioning had made him
lose his nerve for the moment, and he wanted his nerve still. Things that were
dangerous had to be destroyed. He winced.
He hated the idea of even touching them.
Yet it had to be done. He realized that, and when he had
locked the door of his library, he opened the secret press into which he had
thrust Basil hallwoods coat and bag. A huge fire was blazing. He piled another
log on it. The smell of the singing clothes and burning leather was horrible.
It took him 3/4 of an hour to consume everything. At the end he felt faint and
sick, and having lit some Algerian pases in a pierced copper braia he bathed his
hands and forehead with a cool musk scented vinegar.
Suddenly he started. His eyes grew strangely bright, and he gwed nervously
at his under lip Between two of the windows stood a large Florentine cabinet,
made out of ebony and inlaid with ivory and blue lapis. He watched it as though
it were a thing that could fascinate and make afraid, as though it held something
that he longed for and yet almost loathed. His breath quickened. A mad
craving came over him. He lit a cigarette and then threw it away. His eyelids
drooped till the long fringed lashes almost touched his cheek. But he still
watched the cabinet. At last he got up from the sofa on which he had been lying,
went over to it, and having unlocked it, touched some hidden spring. A triangular
draw passed slowly out. His fingers moved instinctively towards it, dipped in, and closed on
something. It was a small Chinese Bo of black and Gold Dust lacquer, elaborately
wrought, the sides patented with curved waves, and the silken cords hung with
round crystals and tassled in platted metal threads. He opened it. Inside was a
green paste, waxy in luster the odor curiously heavy and
persistent. He hesitated for some moments, with a strangely immobile smile upon his
face. Then shivering, though the atmosphere of the room was terribly hot,
he drew himself up and glanced at the clock. It was 20 minutes to 12 He put the
box back, shutting the cabinet doors as he did so, and went into his
bedroom. As midnight was striking bronze blows upon the dusky air, Dorian Gray,
dressed commonly, and with a muffler wrapped around his throat, crept quietly
out of his house. In Bon Street he found a handsome with a good horse. He hailed
it and in a low voice gave the driver an
address. The man shook his head. “It is too far for me,” he
muttered. “Here is a sovereign for you,” said Dorian. “You shall have another if you drive
fast.” “All right, sir,” answered the man, “you will be there in an hour,” and after his
fair had got in he turned his horse round and drove rapidly towards the
river and E chapter 16